[Music]
hi and welcome to this what's new
session on subscription billing my name
is Brian Nelson I'm a program manager
within the business Central Development
team and I'll take you through the new
feature for subscription billing or
subscription and recurring
billing we have added a new
module um for subscription and for
subscription handling for recurring
invoicing um it has a set of new
Concepts that it'll probably take a
while to uh to get used
to uh a slightly different process
because it is uh a different thing
there's a concept of contracts which you
would normally expect when you have uh a
subscription you have a contract for
what it is that you will get recurring
invoices for you have service
commitments uh which specify the thing
that you will be invoiced for like it
can be um tickets minutes usage of
something uh or just a a service that is
provided to you on a recurring basis
there are some objects behind it with
prices and
costs um and maybe some other linked uh
Service uh
commitments you can generate uh billing
proposals uh or
schedules uh once you have a contract
once you have a setup uh you can get the
system to generate um either the next uh
invoice or the next set of invoices or
you can do the next invoice for an
extended period if you need to it's very
flexible in in what you can do there you
can also um do use a space building
which means that you will get the
quantities and maybe also the prices
uh that you invoice from an external
system imported into these contracts and
then start your recurring billing
process later on we will automate these
processes so that you just need to set
them up and it will
run um once you post an invoice for a
recurring uh or for a subscription it
may be for a service that extends 12
months like if it's an annual fee for a
service that you provide right but you
in your accounting system you only
recognize the the revenue for the
individual periods so there is a
deferrals um system for these contracts
that set up the deferrals in advance
when you post uh a new invoice and then
you can decide to release the individual
periods the ferals and then post the
revenue to G or expense if it's on the
vendor side
you can manage prices you can do updates
to contracts we will see that in the
demo you can do renewals uh you can even
automate some of it um and later on in
the minor release I think it's
25.2 we will have a popi app which means
we will have embedded reporting for the
subscription billing module and we will
also provide some Excel reports so you
can get your data out and do a quick
analysis or maybe even create your own
reports uh based on that
there's a lot more to learn because it's
a a new module there are some new terms
and and new ways of doing
things um but we will see some of that
in the coming demos so the first demo is
uh a customer that comes in and want
your Hardware that is sold with
maintenance two different flavors of
Maintenance and then we will uh create
the contract and create the billing
proposal and we'll see the first invo
and then we'll look at the deferrals so
we see it how it's done end to end in a
very straightforward scenario and then
later on we can extend the contract with
some more services that we can then
build going forward but let's start with
um a sales
order we'll create a new
one we'll create it for tail spin
and
um just to keep it relatively simple we
um do it for
June all good and then we have to pick
an item and in this case we have a a
hardware item here the hardware it comes
with maintenance and we have two kinds
of Maintenance that we have set up for
this Hardware you can either select the
internal
ones uh whether that's the premium or
standard ones it's debatable but there's
also one that is done by an external
vendor um slightly different prices but
you get to select in the sales process
or the customer gets to
select uh in this case where you only
have a vendor there's only a customer
side like selling side like we're doing
the support so we'll pick that
one and we need a
quantity of one
we have a th000 in total but we also
sold maintenance and that's not
reflected
anywhere and that is because it's a
service commitment that we will build on
a recurring basis we have
maintenance uh the price is 1,000 there
are some calculation types in this case
we've chosen the item price you could
also choose the item price including
discounts and in this case the item
price is 1,000 mainten is is 20% of that
so that's 200 and it's done you can see
here the billing uh base period is 12
months so it's annual and the billing
rhythm is also uh annual which makes uh
sense of course so an annual fee you
could say for maintenance service so we
have the order but we still don't have a
contract we still don't have these
recurring invoices so they need to sort
of come into play and they will come
into play when you start uh releasing
the order uh either by shipping or
releasing or also when you uh ship an
invoice and in our case there are no
extra services or anything we can just
go ahead and ship an invoice but before
we do that let's take a look at the
order confirmation that we could send to
the
customer there is a separate uh word
layout or designated word word layout
for or subscription billing because it
has to have extra
information we'll pick that and do
preview and as you can see it looks like
a normal uh sales order and it has a a
unit price 1,000 and then it has a
service price uh that is a recurring
service and that is what we will see
going forward so for this one we can
just say Post shipping invoice
and we say no like the invoice is there
for for
Hardware so now we've invoice the order
they have um gotten an invoice for the
hardware but now we need to in the
coming months we need to uh invoice for
the maintenance
service we would normally go into uh
recurring billing we would set the date
um it started in June so we would expect
to see something here
uh but there's nothing there's other
customers because the service commitment
that we have has not been assigned to a
contract
yet uh we have tailpin toys
here uh but it hasn't been assigned to a
contract so you can either pick an
existing one if there is one or if it's
a completely new uh customer you would
probably go in and U Pick them and say
uh here's a contract
and okay with that and then you assign
the selected services to the contract
and it will disappear so now we have a
contract for tailes spin
toys and then we could go into recurring
billing clear this
proposal the first building template is
a filter for which contracts Do you want
to build and periods and so forth but
for now we'll just focus on on June we
we don't set an end date because we want
whatever is next for these customers so
we create a billing proposal and we can
see that tailes spin toys is in the list
with a period from June to end of May
next year because it was an annual
maintenance contract so um let's focus
on that and we can then uh create
documents we are on this line we can
create
document and um we can put in
for these documents and we can decide to
either have them here or we can post
them directly we can uh do an invoice or
a document per contract per the uh sell
to customer or the bill to customer so
there's flexibility in in what you uh
generate out of this for now we'll just
uh do it per
contract so let's do that we'll also
create the the rest of uh these
contracts that were out there on this
date which is fine um we'll go to the
sales
invoices and we have tailes spin toys
here we would expect to see posting date
end of
June and there's a description Hardware
it's the maintenance part the it's for
the full period it cost uh 200 which is
20% of the cost before you post um maybe
you want to see where does this uh
invoice end up because it is an annual
invoice and you can do posting preview
and first you can see there are two
entries in deal we'll look at them
first and you can see that we post the
receivables the customer part they got
an invoice and then we post directly to
deferrals because it's not obvious that
you want to recognize any or all of it
or maybe part of it
um right away but we have set up
customer contract deferrals and we have
12 we started at the beginning of a
period so there's no
partial
periods um and they're here and um
they're ready to be released is a field
whether they are released or not whether
they have been moved to to GL or not and
they they split out the 200 for the
maintenance for the annual maintenance
in in 12
periods so they they will be generated
here and enough posting then we'll post
the invoice
and
um we could go to um the posted
invoice then we could say find entries
it would of course be the same as we saw
in in preview we could uh look up the
deferrals a better way of uh looking at
The Furs rather than checking some dates
is to look at how they are split out in
future month and we are missing a year
here posting date month I'll pick the
year because we didn't start in January
in this year we will only defer in in
June and going forward up until May next
year so here we have next
year and you have entries there but that
is the deferral entries nothing has been
posted to GL yet so now we have posted
the invoice with the annual subscription
and we have the deferral entries in
order to get the deferral entries from
the deferral account that I posted now
to the revenue account we need to
release the deferrals and that is done
through a batch job so we go to
contract
deferral
release it's a bad job and we will do it
for um we could do it only for June and
it would be fine but we could also say
assuming that our accounting periods are
open uh say that we do it for uh August
and then we would have June July and
August uh released for deferrals so we
put it in and we have it and then we
could go back to our deferrals entries
customer
contract uh
deferrals and if we filter on only this
contract that we looked at before and we
say filter to this value before we look
at the pivot we you can see that for
this contract for those that are
released uh we can actually spread it
out here we can see that the ones that
are released are in June July and August
and the
rest is for the remaining uh period of
the invoice
including um May next year has not been
uh released so we can control what we
release uh or what part of the reeven
you we recognize in in DL based on these
contracts so we have started with an
order we have invoiced the uh customer
for the hardware we have uh created a
service commitment the commitment to
provide maintenance service we have
taken that commitment and put it into a
contract we have created a billing
proposal uh for uh the next uh invoicing
period which happened to be in June but
the invoice that came out of that was
for full year because the maintenance is
an annual
subscription after that um when you post
the invoice because it's an annual uh
subscription uh deferral entries are
created and you can then release them uh
in a batch job where you control what to
release and and when so that's all good
you have a a sales process and you can
can do recurring billing sometimes the
customer will come in and want something
more or maybe you're not selling
Hardware but just some services so of
course you can start from a
contract it can either be from um a
completely new contract or maybe the
customer uh in this case tailes spin
toys they just want uh an addition to
their contract and you cannot just add
lines but you can extend a
contract because you cannot just add any
random uh line to a contract you can
only add uh service
commitments like things that we can uh
do recurring billing for so in this case
we extend this contract and in this case
they don't need more um ticketed support
um but maybe they want premium
support and
um it
cost U they just want one of that it
cost 108
and they want it to start let's say um
in
September and then we can see what uh
happens here but now that you've done
that um you can extend the uh contract
and you have a new line added to the
contract it can also be from a
completely blank contract for a new
customer uh it's more often the case
that there are modifications to an
existing um product if it was the case
that there was a standard support
included you can put an end dat to the
to any of these services so that you can
add more and stop some of the uh
existing uh items so now we have um a
new service commitment on this contract
so now we can go to recurring billing we
could pick uh end of November as the
next billing date let's say we skipped
September and October for a reason we
want a billing proposal for end of nov M
so there are some existing lines here
and they are already tied to uh to
existing documents we can see that over
here so we cannot easily delete them
we'll leave them but we'll create a
billing proposal where we expect
tailspin to show up and they're here the
new service with the support premium
support starts in um in September and
runs until billing to date uh end of
November and then we could say we create
documents and create
documents and we could uh create it
let's just
create two documents because some of
them are already uh existing let's go
and
see invoice Tail
Spin and we now have uh an invoice for
premium support for September October
and November like three times
180 so there are different ways of
starting the process but the end result
is of course always an
invoice with the feral entries uh that
will also be the case here because it's
an extended
period and revenue
recognition um so it's very flexible uh
what you can do and what you can set up
uh in this in this release um you will
have to do with the analysis mode and
the list but in the 25.2 minor we will
provide Excel reports so you can get
your data out and do analysis and you'll
also uh see the powerbi embed app that
will be provided uh so you will have
embedded reporting for subscription
billing in business
Central sometimes when you do
subscription billing or recurring
invoicing the data for the individual
invoices are based uh off of some
external data um usually what the End
customer assumes it could be support
ticket support
minutes uh articles read um how much
electricity that they have
consumed um different uh kinds of
consumption and of course you need to
feed that data into the individual
invoices for the recurring
billing and this is what usage based
billing can do for you let's look at the
product and see how it's
done so when you've done your setup with
the data supplier with the item
references you're ready to import some
data and you can search for it or you
can uh bookmark it like I did so we have
us this data import here it's a simple
process uh you want to do a new
import you need to um edit the record so
we point to A supplier of data then you
import the file that you
have so now we get the file in
you can see here to the right that we
have one file in you can then either um
step by step go through the process of
creating the imported line process them
uh create the billing data and then
process the billing data you can also
delete it again if there was a mistake
but this is a good way of of going
through it uh when you are doing
troubleshooting uh if it's just a normal
process and you've done it before you
will just go and process data
and everything is okay here in this case
I have one line uh is for February I
could put a note on that um tickets
February 24 part one for example then I
can uh go back to recurring bilding and
create new proposals uh it will take the
data that it has here for that
subscription and create uh a new invoice
I can also create all the invoices if I
want that uh directly by creating
customer invoices there's also a button
or action for uh vendor
invoices now that I know that there's
just one invoice uh I can just go and do
it here I know it's for
February and we'll just keep it unposted
so we can go and take a look at it it is
created and then we just take a look at
it it's
here this one so we got it um eight
tickets they used up in support and
we're going to charge them in this
invoice for February the period is down
here so it's all very easy once you've
set it up to get data in if you have
data and they come from an exter
external system and you haven't set up
the contract for the customer the
process is almost the same you create a
new import
and we'll just edit it pick the
supplier and we'll import the uh a new
file actually I know that we will be
looking at tickets for January 24 part
three then I can import a
file and once it imported I can process
it
but because I process data without
having having a contract already uh the
system will give me an error and I can
just click on that error it will say
there's no um subscription ID for the uh
for the service commitment it has
identified the service commitment
but um it doesn't know in what contract
to put it so we'll extend the
contract we don't need the vendor part
of it we need a
customer we only have we actually we
want a new contract for this
one we
want
Lucan and we're good to go so now we we
created a contract that we can put it
in we'll pick
that and the system has picked up that
it's still ticketed support um the
provision start that's the beginning
date in this file is 1st of January and
uh like the example uh before it has a
quantity already in the file so we'll
pick that um in order to extend a new
contract you need to perform extensions
first it's fast and then you can close
it you can go
back and then you can process data once
more and you're good to go and we could
create a customer
invoice in this case it was for
January we'll keep it open so we can
take a look at
it and from here you can actually go
directly and uh see the customer
contracts you can also navigate to open
uh invoices but you can see the invoices
here directly it's for Lucan and we
would expect to see a quantity of six in
here so whether you have uh the
contracts already or you need to do a
mapping it's a straightforward uh
process with little setup uh needed in
terms of getting started and um
importing usage
data so a brief demonstration of some of
the capabilities there's a lot more and
there's a lot more flexibility there's a
lot more variance and variations that
can be supported um it's a new module
there are some new
terminology uh but it supports uh
recurring billing for uh
Services you can start from an order and
so you have a sales order process or you
can start directly with uh contracts if
that's your your business you can also
use uses data and import it and then do
recurring billing on that there's a
deferral part so that you recognize
Revenue um the way that you want it will
split up the um uh invoices in deferrals
and and you can put them or take them
into GL uh in the way that you prefer
there are reports coming in Excel and
powerbi so go and take a test drive of
the new module thanks for watching this
session